So
what is the minimum level of virtue and
precepts for someone who aspires to
understand the dharma? And why can't you
just understand the four noble truths
with with less than that? Why is it a
ver why is virtue an indispensable
prerequisite for true understanding?
Isn't it just a matter of clearly seeing
the things that are already there?
Uh it is a matter of clearly seeing
things that are already there. However,
you can't see them because they're
obscured, obstructed,
covered up, wrapped up in your unh
wholesome, unbeneficial behavior.
So until that behavior is purified,
what what is there is not those things
that you want to see.
So things that that that that you need
to understand like the root of the
suffering and so on uh are there but are
simply obscured. So when you look at
them you're seeing something else.
So the problem people have with that is
that oh well but how can I know how can
I know that being virtuous
would make me understand? Well, by being
virtuous that's the problem is like that's shows
that's the problem is like that's shows
you the limits of the reason you know I
said that before when the Buddha said
you know the dharma cannot be attained
by the mere reasoning alone doesn't mean
you need to become unreasonable
doesn't need to become like you need to
become mystical and just ignore the
basic principles of thought no it means
they needs it needs another another
aspect to be as an input there so you
keep your reason but amplify it
and you can't pre-reason
the virtue as an amplifier of reason.
You need to do it.
But people want to find a reasonable I
mean you could obviously reason that
virtue would probably be helpful but you
can't know for sure. The only way to
know what virtue does to your reason is
to start keeping the virtue while trying
to understand the dharma with your
reason. I looking for the meaning
looking for the for the root principle
the the universal nature of things and
so on. So the whole point of the of that
virtue is really
to create this dimension that doesn't
exist in you because you don't have the
virtue. The dimension of confined mind
that is then outlined in and of itself
not scattered.
And that can only be done through
certain mode of behavior.
Eight precepts, sense, restraint,
moderation, what we go on and on and on
and on about. Um,
and only really the only question you
need to ask yourself is what do I have
to lose?
So you say, "Yeah, but I still want to
know before I start doing it whether it
will be a guaranteed success." It was
like, well, the only way to know it is
to start doing it. Same, you know, the
similar of the the two friends, one goes
on top of the mountain, another one's at
the bottom, says, "What do you see up
there?" And says, "I see seas and
mountains." And I was like, "I don't see
anything." I turn around, I don't see
anything. I want you to show me what you
see without me needing to climb the
mountain. Well, that's impossible. But
as I said, just ask yourself, what do I
have to lose?
What do I have to lose if I stop
killing or thinking unh wholesome
thoughts of harm? What do I have to lose
if I stop lying or or thinking, you
know, engaging in forms of deceit and so
on? What do I have to lose if I stop
scratching the itch like a rabid monkey?
Sensual itch. What do I have to lose if
I withdraw from sensuality?
withdraw from from from pressure, pain,
thirst. That's that's not very calming
nor peaceful.
What do I have to lose if I stop taking
intoxicants? What do I have to lose if I
focused on honesty and transparency?
It's like nothing. I'm actually gaining.
Plus, if I keep trying to understand the
dharma, I might get that dimension that
cannot be attained through mere
reasoning alone.
So, it's a win-win either way.